Guide to the Rose Pastor Stokes Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
162 --- Sen Katayama; graduate of Yale Divinity School, 1895; Head of Japanese Communist Party; member of the Executive Committee of the Comintern; portrait probably given to Rose Pastor Stokes when she served as a delegate to the 4th Congress of the Communist International, November-December 1922, Leninigrad (Petrograd)-Moscow
163 --- Newspaper announcement of second marriage of J. G. P. Stokes, March 13, 1926 [Removed to Printed Material, Series III, Box No. 8, Folder No. 8.]
164 --- Memorial Service at New Star Casino, 107th Street & Park Avenue, New York City, July 24, 1933, in honor of Rose Pastor Stokes, Sergei Gussev and Clara Zetkin (German Communist Party Leader), staged by Communist Party of the United States.
165 --- Memorial Service - girl carrying funeral urn with ashes of Rose Pastor Stokes sent back from Germany where she had died at Frankfort. Addition 1974 Jan.
166 --- Portrait of Rose Pastor Stokes dancing by Clarence Hudson White, 1909 - "Caritas Island"
167 --- Portrait of R. P. S. dancing by Clarence Hudson White, 1909
168 --- View of "Caritas Island" from Wallack's Point (Lederle House) taken by Rena Woodward Parker, 1914, while visiting Mrs. John R. MacNeille
169 --- Portrait of James Graham Phelps Stokes in his Library, "Caritas Island", 1909, by Clarence Hudson White
170 --- Helen Phelps Stokes at her desk, New York City home of Anson P. Stokes
171 --- Studio portrait of Marie Rauh (1906), girlhood friend of R. P. S. in Cleveland, Ohio
172 --- Portrait of girlhood friend of R. P. S. in Cleveland, Ohio
173 --- Group photograph of members of Industrial Workers of the World at the silk strike, 1913, at Patterson, New Jersey - Strike leaders Patrick Quinlan, Carlo Tresca, Elizabeth Gurley Flynn, Adolf Lessig and William D. Haywood (Quinlan visited on "Caritas Island")
174 --- View of Stokes house from the quarry garden, "Caritas Island"- R. P. S. seated in the center
175 --- Path by end of Stokes House
176 --- Children in Cleveland, Ohio
177 --- Olive tiford Dargan in cornfield, North Carolina
178 --- Child bathing in sandy beach cove, "Caritas Island"
179 --- Rose Pastor Stokes - portrait taken in the 1920's
180 --- Mrs. Walter Weyl (Bertha Poole), Walter Weyl and child Nathaniel Weyl
181 --- Rose Pastor Stokes with friends at end of bridge, "Caritas Island"
182 --- South elevation, Stokes House
183 --- Rose garden near bridge, "Caritas Island"
184 --- R. P. S. and relatives bathing on rocks
185 --- Mr. and Mrs. Frederick Alonzo King (friend at University Settlement) and children on the rocks, "Caritas Island"
186 --- Frederick A. King
187 --- J. G. P. Stokes on steamship
188 --- W. E. Walling House, SW elevation, "Caritas Island"
189 --- J. G. P. Stokes flying a kite from driveway, "Caritas Island"
190 --- Gathering at Sherwood Forest, near Baltimore - Intercollegiate Socialist Society meeting, Sep. 1916
191 --- Leroy Scott House, Boat House, "Caritas Island"
192 --- Sandy beach cove used for swimming, "Caritas Island"
193 --- Isthmus connecting "Caritas Island" at low tide to outer island and breakwater
194 --- South elevation, Stokes House
195 --- Cedar tree looking towards Sound, "Caritas Island"
196 --- View towards Wallack's Point (Belden House) from driveway
197 --- Quarry garden with Stokes House beyond
198 --- Class of 1895, Divinity School, Yale University, including Sen Katayama (later head of Japanese Communist Party and COMINTERN leader)
199 --- Sen Katayama (close-up), Divinity School class, Yale
200 --- William E. Walling House, entrance elevation (SE), "Caritas Island"
201 --- Portrait of Ethel Todd Ponselle, who rented Walling House, 1916
202 --- Portrait of Robert Rives LaMonte, Socialist Party theorist
203 --- Porch, Stokes House
204 --- Portrait of Mabel Dunlap Curry, wife of Terre Haute professor - Secretary of Theodore Debs, friend of R. P. S. and close friend of Eugene Debs (she visited Debs at Atlanta Federal Penitentiary
205 --- Mr. and Mrs. Curry and infant at Terre Haute, Indiana, when first married (Prof. Charles Madison Curry)
206 --- "Graham" (J. G. P. Stokes) as a boy
207 --- Unidentified friends or relatives of Mr. and Mrs. Stokes
208 --- Jeannette Pearl (wife of Louis Fraina) as a girl. Fraina later changed his name to Lewis Corey and taught at Antioch College; he had a long career in the Syndicalist and Communist movement
209 --- Lillian and William Fletcher in swimming
210 --- Swimmers at "Caritas' Island"
211 --- Portrait of Helen Todd (sister of Ethel Todd Ponselle); feminist
212 --- Helen Todd near Scott House, "Caritas Island"
213 --- Mrs. and Mr. William Earl Dodge Stokes (brother of Anson Phelps Stokes)
214 --- Portrait of Peagram Dargan (as Harvard University student). He was the husband of Olive Tilford Dargan. He was a poet; he commited suicide at sea in 1915, off the coast of Cuba
215 --- Matilda Rabinowitz (Robbins) at Akron (Ohio) Rubber Company strike, 1913; she was a friend of Rose Pastor Stokes and a political agitator
216 --- Allan Fletcher (son of Lillian Pastor Fletcher) and his Aunt Daisy
217 --- Sundial in front of Stokes House, "Caritas Island"
218 --- Portrait of Maxim Gorky, New York City, 1906
219 --- Chalet (Guest House),"Summerbrook"
220 --- House, "Summerbrook"
221 --- Visitors at "Summerbrook"; John Spargo, center rear
222 --- Visitors at "Summerbrook"
223 --- Visitor with Borzoi at "Summerbrook"
225 --- Tether-ball game, "Summerbrook"; Upton Sinclair on the right
226 --- 4TH COMINTERN CONGRESS - Train with foreign delegates arrives at Petrograd Rairoad Station (November 14, 1922) - Clara Zetkin of the German Communist Party with muff; Rose Pastor Stokes, a U. S. Communist Party delegate, wearing black fur hat and white fur coat; Gregory Zinoviev wearing fur hat at right Box 10 Folder 24a
226A --- Train with foreign delegates which include: Karl Radek (Poland), Hugo Urbahns (Hamburg), Hugo Eberlein (Ger.)
226B --- Train with foreign delegates which include: Werner Scholem (Ger.), Paul Boettcher (Ger.), Fritz Heckert (Ger.) Willi Munzenberg (Ger.), Ernst Meyer (Ger.)
227 --- U. S. Communist Party members on the steps of the Petrograd Railroad Station arriving for the opening sessions of the 4th Comintern Congress - Delegate Rose Pastor Stokes in center wearing black fur hat; Max Eastman stands directly behind her; Yevdokimov (member of the Petrograd Soviet) greets delegates; Mrs. Stokes is framed by Zinoviev at the left and Lunacharsky at the right (carrying suitcase) Box 10 Folder 24a
228 --- 4TH COMINTERN CONGRESS - Moscow - Group of U.S. Delegates, including Rose Pastor Stokes
229 --- 4TH COMINTERN CONGRESS - Celebration of 5th Anniversary of Bolshevik Revolution. Group includes Joseph Stalin, Zinoviev, Clara Zetkin (Ger.), Kalinin, Sen Katayama (Japan) (Yale Divinity School, B.D. 1895.) --- note Photographs #226, 226A, 226B, 227, 228, 229 were printed from an original news reel of film taken in USSR by news-cameraman DZIGA VERTOV, covering events related to the 4th COMINTERN CONGRESS held in Moscow- PETROGRAD, NOV.-DEC. 1922. Herman Axelbank (Historic Film Archive, 2720 Hering Avenue, Bronx, New York City); Recently (1980) the original newsreel films were acquired by the HOOVER INSTITUTION, Stanford, California. Photographs listed above are copies of originals.
230 --- CLUB EMBLEM (enamelled) "FRIENDLY CLUB", Cleveland, Ohio Inscribed: Nov. 1895 "Rose" - July 18, 1905 (date of RP's marriage to Graham Stokes)
231 --- Reversed side of EMBLEM with engraving
232 --- Reversed side of EMBLEM with engraving
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
With the excepction of Box 9, Folders 12, 13, and 18, materials in Series 1-4 are avaiable on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 45 instead of the original copies.
African Americans -- Social conditions; Birth control; Communism; Radicalism; Socialism; Women artists; Women poets; Women; Diaries; Authors; Abbott, Leonard Dalton, 1878-1953; Anderson, Sherwood, 1876-1941; Ashley, Jessie; Brodsky, Joseph R., 1890-1947; Curry, Mabel Dunlop; Dargan, Olive Tilford, 1869-1968; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Eastman, Max, 1883-1969; Fawcett, James Waldo, 1893-1968; Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947; Gibran, Kahlil, 1883-1931; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Laidler, Harry W. (Harry Wellington), 1884-1970; Lunacharsky, Anatoly Vasilievich, 1875-1933; Nearing, Scott, 1883-1983; Ornitz, Samuel, 1890-1957; Quinlan, Patrick; Romaine, Jerome Isaac; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966; Spargo, John, 1876-1966; Spofford, William B.; Stokes, James Graham Phelps, 1872-1960; Stokes, Rose Pastor, 1879-1933; Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1872-1949; Wald, Lillian D., 1867-1940; Walling, William English, 1877-1936; Williams, Albert Rhys, 1883-1962; Communist Party of the United States of America; Intercollegiate Socialist Society; Communist International. Congress (4th) -- Leningrad and Moscow -- 1922
- Correspondence, 1905-1906, 1908-1909, 1912-1933; Series I; 1.75 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  CORRESPONDENCE is arranged in three sections: General Correspondence, Family Correspondence, and Correspondence of Others. Folders are arranged alphabetically by correspondent or by the name of a business or organization. Letters within the folders are arranged chronologically.
  General Correspondence contains considerable correspondence under the headings "Birth Control," "Political Organizations," "Patrick Quinlan Case," and "Writings of RPS," in addition to the correspondence of the persons named on the preceding pages.
  Family Correspondence contains extensive correspondence between Rose Pastor Stokes and each of her two husbands, James Graham Phelps Stokes and Jerome Isaac Romaine. There is also correspondence with Anson Phelps Stokes, brother of James, who was at the time Secretary to Yale University. The remaining correspondence is with Rose Pastor Stokes' mother, half brothers Maurice, Bernard, and Robert, half sister Lillian, step-son Jerry, sister-in-law Helen and other family members.
  Correspondence of Others consists primarily of the correspondence of Jerome Romaine, some of which bears the signature Victor J. Jerome, Romaine's alias. In addition, there is correspondence pertaining to Rose Pastor Stokes' unfinished autobiography.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials in this series are avaiable on microfilm. Patrons must use FILM HM 45 instead of the original copies.
  - General Correspondence
    - A., 1915, 1917, 1930-1932, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abbott, Leonard D. (includes photostat), 1915-1916, 1931-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      General note
      See also: box 1, folder 8
    - Aptheker, Jeanette Zevin, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ashley, Jessie, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - B., 1913-1918, 1920, 1923, 1928-1929, 1932-1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Barnard, Kate (includes xerox copy), 1916, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bedacht, Max, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Birth Control: Birth Control Committee, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      General
      See also: box 3, folder 88
      See also: box 4, folder 133
    - Birth Control: National Birth Control League, 1916-1918 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Birth Control: petition for Margaret Sanger, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Birth Control: Woman's Committee of One Hundred, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Boudin, L.B. (includes photostat), 1917 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Brodsky, Joseph R. and Mrs., 1931, 1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - C., 1913, 1915-1918, 1922, 1927-1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Carney, Jack, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - The Civic Club, 1917, 1927-1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cohen, Maximilian, 1932, n.y. (Box 1, Folder 17)
      See also: Correspondence of Others
    - Committee on Public Information, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Cooke, Joanna F., 1914, 1926, 1928, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Corder, Minnie Federman, 1925-1926, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Curry, Mabel Dunlop, 1918-1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Curry, Mabel Dunlop (photostats), 1928-1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - D., 1913-1914, 1916-1917, 1928, 1930, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Dargan, Olive, 1906-1919 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Dargan, Olive Tilford, 1920-1927, 1930-1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
    - Davis, Ruth Helen, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 27)
      See also: box 3, folder 84
      See also: box 3, folder 83
    - Debs, Eugene V. (includes photostats), 1918, 1919, 1925, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Drawings of RPS, 1926, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Dunn, Robert W., 1916 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - E., 1913, 1916-1917, 1928, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Eastman, Max, undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - F., 1915-1918, 1926, n.d (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Fawcett, James Waldo (includes a photostat), 1921-1922 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Flynn, Elizabeth Gurley (includes photostats), 1918, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Ford, Henry (includes photostats), 1915 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - G., 1915-1918, 1923, 1925-1927, 1932, n.d (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Gibran, Kahlil, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Giovannitti, Arturo (includes photostat), 1916 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Goldman, Emma (includes 3 photostats), 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - H., 1905, 1913-1918, 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - I., 1917, 1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - J., 1913, 1916, 1923, 1930, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Jerome, Victor J (dummy folder) (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - K., 1913, 1916-1917, 1920, 1923, 1932-1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Kiefer, Daniel (Dank), 1921-1922, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - L., 1913, 1915-1918, 1921, 1923, 1930, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - LaGuardia, Fiorello H., 1927 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Lind, Rosemary S., 1928, 1931-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Lydig, Rita, 1917, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - M., 1914-1919, 1921, 1927, 1930-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Macgonnell, Rose Marie, 1930-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Medical Matters: correspondence re: treatments and cures for cancer, 1930-1932 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Mother Earth Publishing Company, 1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - N. (includes one photostat), 1912, 1916-1917, 1928, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Nearing, Scott, 1915-1916, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - The New York Call, 1915-1917, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - O., undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Ornitz, Sam, 1923, 1932-1933 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - P-Q, 1913, 1916-1917, 1928, 1931, 1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Pearl, Jeanette D. (includes 3 letters in photostat only), 1926-1927, 1930, 1931, 1932-1933, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Political Organizations: A-Z, 1913, 1915-1919, 1921, 1925-1926, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Political Organizations: Intercollegiate Socialist Society Harry W. Laidler, organizaing secretary, 1913-1916, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Political Organizations: Intercollegiate Socialist Society (photostats), 1913, 1917-1921, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Political Organizations: Intercollegiate Socialist Society Josephine Burnham, Secretary NE Comm., 1913 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - "Political Organizations: League for Mutual Aid Adelaide M. Schulkind, Exec. Sec., 1925, 1928-1929, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Political Organizations: National Committe for the Defense of Political Prisoners-Sherwood Anderson, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Political Organizations: The National Social Unit Organization, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Political Organizations: The People's Institute of Brooklyn, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Political Organizations: The Socialist Party, 1914-1918, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Political Organizations: Workers Party of America- C. E. Ruthenberg (1 letter in photostat only), 1923-1925 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Political Organizations: Workers Party of America (1 letter in photostat only), 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Political Organizations: Workers (Communist) Party, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Political Organizations: Communist Party (photostat), 1930 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Quinlan, Patrick (includes photostat), 1921 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Quinlan, Patrick: Legal Case 1st letter to RPS from PQ, 1915-1916 June 5, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Quinlan, Patrick: Letters from people working for the Quinlan Defense Committee (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Quinlan, Patrick: Form letter from RPS giving case history and requesting financial aid (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Quinlan, Patrick: Photo-copy of letter from Strobell & Crane: Quinlan Defense Committee (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Quinlan, Patrick: Responses to requests for financial aid and petition signatures and names of radical ministers (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - R., 1912-1913, 1915-1917, 1921, 1924-1926, 1928 1932, undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Rauh, Flora M., 1915-1918, 1930-1932 (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Renner, Clara, 1931-1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Robinson, Frederic H., 1913 (Box 3, Folder 83)
      See also: box 1, folder 27
    - Robinson, Dr. William J., 1913-1916 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Rose, Bess, 1931-1932, undated (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Russ, Phil, 1927, 1931-1932, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - S., 1906, 1913, 1915-1918, 1921, 1924-1926, 1930-1932, undated (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Sanger, Margaret, 1916-1917, undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Scott, Miriam Finn, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Sinclair, Upton (includes 1 photostat), 1915, 1923, 1924, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Spargo, John, 1916-1917, undated (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Spewack, Sam and Bella, 1932-1933, undated (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Spofford, William B., 1917 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Stedman, Seymour, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Stokes, Rose Pastor (2 letters photostated only), 1905, 1908, 1913, 1915-1919, 1923-1926 (Box 3, Folder 95A)
    - Stokes, Rose Pastor, 1927-1928, 1930-1933, n.d (Box 3, Folder 95B)
    - Strunsky, Rose, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - T., 1913-1917, 1921, 1930, undated (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Traubel, Horace and Anne Montgomerie, 1905, 1909, 1914-1917 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Trautwine, John C. Jr., 1915 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - U-V, 1915-1918 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Unidentified: first names only, or no signatures at all, 1913, 1915-1917, 1920, 1924-1925, 1928, 1930, 1932, undated (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Unidentified Political Correspondence, 1920? (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1930-1933 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - W., 1913-1918, 1920, 1924, 1927-1928, 1930-1931, n.d (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Wald, Lillian D., 1917, 1928, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 105)
      See also: box 5, folder 149
    - Walling, William English, 1917 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Williams, Albert Rhys., undated (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Writings of RPS: Autobiography, 1928, 1931-1932 (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Writings of RPS: Books, 1915-1917, 1932, undated (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Writings of RPS: Letters to/from publishers, 1916, 1917, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Writings of RPS: Newspapers and magazine articles, stories, 1915-1918, 1924-1928, undated (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Writings of RPS: Daily Worker, most correspondence from Alexander Bittleman, 1923-1924, 1926-1927, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Writings of RPS: Photocopies of letters from Daily Worker, 1923, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Writings of RPS: Plays, 1915-1917, 1919, 1924-1927 (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Writings of RPS: Plays: corres. with Washington Square Players, 1915-1917 (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Writings of RPS: Poetry, 1913, 1926, 1928, undated (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - Writings of RPS: Poetry: photocopy of letter from Marcus Graham, July 5, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Writings of RPS: Related Organizations: The Authors' League of America, Inc., 1915, 1917-1918 (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Writings of RPS: Related Organizations: Socialist Press Club, 1915, undated (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Writings of RPS: Related Organizations: The National Board of Review of Motion Pictures, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Writings of RPS: Related Organizations: The Poetry Society, Inc.; and The Poetry Society of America; Anthology of Revolutionary Poetry, 1917, undated (Box 4, Folder 121)
    - X-Y-Z, 1916, 1921, 1928, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Family Correspondence
    - Fletcher, Lillian Pastor, 1928, 1932, undated (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Pastor, Anna (mother), 1916-1917, undated (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Pastor, Bernard (brother) and RPS, 1915, 1918, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - (Pastor, Maurice?), undated (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Pastor, Robert (brother), 1913 (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Romaine, Germinal (Jerome's son), 1930-1932 (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Romaine, Jerome Isaac, 1927-1928, 1930-1933, undated (Box 4, Folder 129-132)
    - Stokes, Anson Phelps (brother-in-law) (includes photostats), 1916 (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - (Stokes, Helen?) (sister-in-law), 1915, 1922, 1925-1926, 1933, undated (Box 4, Folder 134)
    - Stokes, J. Graham Phelps, 1913-1917, 1920-1922, 1925-1926, undated (Box 4, Folder 135-136)
    - Stokes, Rose Pastor, to JIR, 1928, 1930-1933, undated (Box 4, Folder 137-138)
    - Stokes, Rose Pastor, to JGPS, 1913-1916, 1920-1921, 1925-1926 (Box 4, Folder 139)
    - Stokes, Rose Pastor, 1916, 1925, 1928, 1932 (Box 4, Folder 140)
    - Miscellaneous family members: cousin Sherman; niece, Mrs. Agnes Pastor; aunts Sarah Rosenthal, 1904, 1916, 1932, undated (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Correspondence of Others
    - A-Z, 1914, 1917, 1921-1922, 1931-1932, undated (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - Ames, Winthrop, theatrical producer, undated (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Cohen, Maximilian, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Dargan, Olive, 1920, undated (Box 5, Folder 145)
      See also: General Correspondence
    - Laidler, Harry W., 1914 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Lunacharsky, A., letter to Chief of the Musical Dept. of the School for the Blind, Moscow, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Pearl, Jeanette, 1933 (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Romaine, Jerome I. (V.J. Jerome), 1928, 1930-1933, 1936, n.d (Box 5, Folder 149)
    - Romaine, Jerome I., and Dargan, Olive T., 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - RPS Autobiography: includes corres. of Earl Browder, Pascal Corvici, Joseph A, Margolis, Sam Ornitz, Jerome Romaine (includes photostat), 1933-1937 (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - Stokes, J. Graham Phelps, 1916-1924 (Box 5, Folder 152)
      See also: Family Correspondence
    - Strobell, Caro Lloyd, (ISS) includes letter to John Spargo, undated (Box 5, Folder 153)
    - Walling, William English, to JGPS, undated (Box 5, Folder 154)
- Writings, 1900, 1903, 1908-1909, 1912, 1914-1917, 1922, 1926, 1933, 1958; Series II
  The WRITINGS series consists of manuscripts and printed writings arranged alphabetically by subject.
  Among the manuscript materials there are several typewritten political tracts, copies of two speeches, a typewritten opinion on divorce and a short diary for 1933. Included in the printed material are feature columns written for the New York Jewish Daily News, several magazine articles, a few published poems, and some miscellaneous pamphlets.
  Of special interest in the series are a xerox copy of Rose Pastor Stokes' unfinished autobiography, which covers the period from 1879 to 1905, and a copy of Minority Report to be appended to Program and Methods of Approach. The latter is part of a report on the Negro question in America presented to the 4th Comintern Congress, Petrograd-Moscow, 1922. Rose Pastor Stokes was member of the reporting committee and wrote under the nom-de-plume "Sacha."
  Re: Rose Pastor Stokes Autobiography
  1. There is an incomplete first draft of the RPS autobiography and a photocopy of the same in the RPS Papers (MS 573, Series II, Box 6, Folders 6A and 6B).